<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pleasant description of the fortunate ilandes, called the Ilands of Canaria vvith their straunge fruits and commodities. Verie delectable to read, to the praise of God. Composed by the poore pilgrime.</title>
            <author>Nicholas, Thomas, b. ca. 1532.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1583</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17891</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4557</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112725</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847970</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847970</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13041</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17891)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13041)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 238:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pleasant description of the fortunate ilandes, called the Ilands of Canaria vvith their straunge fruits and commodities. Verie delectable to read, to the praise of God. Composed by the poore pilgrime.</title>
                  <author>Nicholas, Thomas, b. ca. 1532.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas East,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1583.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The poore pilgrime = Thomas Nicholas--STC.</note>
                  <note>Printed under Nicholas's name in Richard Hakluyt's "The principal navigations", volume 2 (STC 12626).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A description of the Canarie Ilands.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Canary Islands --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13041:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13041:1"/>
            <p>A PLEASANT deſcription of the fortunate Ilandes, called the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands of CANARIA, vvith their ſtraunge fruits and commodities.</p>
            <p>VERIE DELECTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to read, to the praiſe of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compoſed by the</hi> poore Pilgrime.</p>
            <p>¶Imprinted at London by Thomas Eaſt. 1583.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13041:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13041:2"/>
            <head>¶ TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Maſter Ihon Woolley Eſquire, one of the Secretaries to the Queenes <hi>moſt excellent Maiestie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ore Pilgrimes vſe, Right worſhipfull ſir, that after their wearie iournies, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into their natiue ſoile, to communicate the troth, of anie thing worthie to be knowen and of them ſeene, among their eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall friends which are learned, and alſo louers of ſuch kinde of vocation. The holy ſcripture ſheweth vs, that when the wiſe men called Magi, being led by a ſtraunge ſtarre, to the place where Chriſt our Sauior was borne, at which place the ſtarre did not only ſtaie, but alſo gaue a wonderful bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with ſhining beams, to aſſure them that there the Sauiour was. Vndoubtedly theſe men letted not to declare theſe maruailous things &amp; viſions, at their returne, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth at this preſent, that in Aethiopia &amp; the Eaſt Countries, are an infinite number of Chriſtians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Likewiſe the Eunuch, meſſenger to the Queene of Candace, letted not to manifeſt in his Countrie, the miraculous things that he had ſeene in Ieruſalem when
<pb facs="tcp:13041:3"/>
Chriſt our Redeemer ſuffered the moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death of the croſſe. Nor yet the Queene of Sabba, kept in ſecret the wiſdome of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</p>
            <p>But the cauſe Right worſhipfull, that I tooke this little Pamphlet in hand, was tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the writing of Andrewe Theuet a Frenchman, who wrote of the Fortunate I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landes by heareſay: But I poore Pilgrime maie call thoſe Ilands infortunate: for there was I apprehended for an heretike and an open enimie to the Romiſh Churche, and there deteyned in that bloudie Inquiſition, the ſpace of fiue yeares, &amp; now come home to offer this little worke to your worſhip, becauſe your helping hand is alwaies ready to fauor and further anie vertuous or good attempt. Beſeeching your worſhip to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it, &amp; to conſider that poore Pilgrimes haue not any other thing to giue, &amp; the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie graunt your hearts deſire.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>At commaundement: The</hi> P.P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13041:3"/>
            <head>¶ A DESCRIPTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>of the fortunate Ilandes,</hi> now called the Ilandes of Canaria, with their perticular Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>LATO</hi> in his <hi>Thimeo,</hi> writeth, that about 750. yeres paſt, ther was a great Ilande lieng in the Ocean Sea, in Front of <hi>Hercules</hi> Pillers, which ſtood at that time in the Iland of <hi>Cadez,</hi> this Ilande was called <hi>Atlantica,</hi> which lande by Gods permiſſion ſonke, ſauing certaine I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands which yet remaine called the Ilands of <hi>Cabo Verde,</hi> the Ilands of <hi>Canaria,</hi> and the Ilands of <hi>Azores</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>The opinion of <hi>Plato</hi> ſéemeth to be true, becauſe the Coaſt of <hi>Grunea</hi> hath ſands &amp; ſhallowes lying out a great way into the maine Ocean, which agréeth as parcell appertayning to the other Ilandes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearſed. Some of the <hi>Canaria</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands as the Ile of <hi>Fortauentura</hi> by name, lyeth 50. leagues diſtaunt from the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent land of <hi>Africa,</hi> and the Ilands of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zores</hi> néere 300. leagues.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13041:4"/>The opinion of <hi>Plato</hi> ſhall ſerue for this purpoſe, to the which I remit me. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe mine inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is, particularly to ſpeak of the <hi>Canaria</hi> Ilands, which are ſeuen in number, wherein I dwelt the ſpace of vij. yeares and more, becauſe I finde ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie in ſundry writers, &amp; eſpecially great vntrothes, in a booke called the new found worlde Antartike, ſet out by a French man called <hi>Andrew Theuet,</hi> the which his booke he dedicated to the Cardinall of <hi>Sens,</hi> keeper of the gteat ſeale of <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It appeareth by the ſaid booke that hée had read y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works of ſundrie philoſophers, Aſtronomers, &amp; Coſmographers, whoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions he gathered together. But touching his owne trauaile which hée affirmeth, I referre to the iudgement of the experient in our daies, and therefore for mine owne part I write of theſe <hi>Canaria</hi> Ilandes, as time hath taught me in manie yeares.</p>
            <div type="description_of_island">
               <head>The Iland of Canaria.</head>
               <p>THE Iland of <hi>Canaria</hi> is almoſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable in length to breadth, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning 12. leagues in length, touching the which as principall &amp; the reſidue, the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13041:4"/>
hold opinion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they diſcouered it in their nauigation toward <hi>America,</hi> but the <hi>Portingals</hi> ſay, that their nation firſt found the ſaid Ilandes, in their Nauigation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Aethiopia</hi> and Eaſt <hi>India.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But truth it is that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> firſt conquered theſe Ilands, with diuers Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Gentlemen in their companie, whoſe deſcendents this preſent daie inioyeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Some write that this Iland was named <hi>Canaria</hi> by meane of the number of dogs which there were found. As for example, <hi>Andrew Theuet</hi> ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one <hi>Iuba</hi> carryed two dogges from thence: but that opinion could I neuer learne by anie of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall people of the Countrie, although I haue talked with many in my time, &amp; with many of their children. For truth it is, that there were dogges, but ſuch as are in all the Norweſt lands, and ſome parte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Weſt <hi>India,</hi> which ſerued the people in ſtéed of ſhéepe for victuall. But of ſome of the conquerours of thoſe Ilandes I haue heard ſay, that the reaſon why they were called <hi>Canaria</hi> Ilands, is, there groweth generally in them all, a foure ſquare cane in great multitude together, which in tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them wil caſt out a liquor as white
<pb facs="tcp:13041:5"/>
as milke, which liquor is ranke poyſon, and at the firſt entrie into theſe Ilandes, ſome of the diſcouerers were therewith poyſoned: for many yeares after that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, the inhabitants began to plant both wine and Sugar, ſo that <hi>Canaria</hi> was not ſo called by Sugar canes.</p>
               <p>The people which firſt inhabited this lande were called <hi>Canaries</hi> by the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, they were clothed in goate ſkinnes made like vnto a looſe caſſocke, they dwelt in caues in the Rockes, in great amitie &amp; brotherly loue. They ſpake all one lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, their chiefe féeding was gelt dogs, goates, and goates milke, their bread was made of Barlie meale and Goats milke, called <hi>Gofia,</hi> which they vſe at this daie, and thereof I haue eaten diuerſe times, for it is accounted excéeding wholeſome.</p>
               <p>Touching the originall of theſe people, ſome holde opinion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the <hi>Romanes</hi> which dwelt in <hi>Africa</hi> exiled them thether, as well men as women, their tongues béeing cutte out of their heades, for blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie againſt the Romane Gods. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it were, their language was ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and not mixed with Romane ſpéech or Arabian.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13041:5"/>This Iland is now the principalleſt of all the reſt, not in fertilitie, but by reaſon it is the ſeate of Iuſtice and gouernment of all the reſidue. This Ilande hath a ſpeciall Gouernor for the Iland onely, yet notwithſtanding there are thrée Iudges called Auditours, who are ſuperiour Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and all in one iointly procéede as the Lord Chanceller of anie realme.</p>
               <p>To this Citie from all the other I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands come al ſuch by appeale, as haue ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained any wrong, and theſe good Iudges doo remedie the ſame. The Citie is called <hi>Ciuitas Palmarum,</hi> it hath a beautifull Cathedrall Church, with all dignities therevnto pertaining. For the publike weale of the Iland ther are ſundrie Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of great authoritie, who haue a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell houſe by themſelues. The Citie is not onely beautifull, but the citizens curious and gallant in apparell. And after anie raine or foule weather a man maye goe cleane in Veluet ſlippers, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground is ſandie, the aire verie temperate, without extreame heat or colde.</p>
               <p>They reape wheate in Februarie, and againe in Maie, which is excellent good, &amp; maketh bread as white as ſnow. This I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<pb facs="tcp:13041:6"/>
hath in it other thrée faire townes, the one called <hi>Telde,</hi> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond <hi>Galder</hi> the third <hi>Guia.</hi> It hath alſo 12. Sugar houſes called <hi>Iugenios,</hi> in which they make great quantitie of good ſugar.</p>
               <p>The manner of the growth of Sugar is in this ſort, a good ground giueth ſoorth fruit nine times in 18. yéere. That is to ſaie, the firſt is called <hi>Planta</hi> which is laid a long in a vorrowe, ſo that the water of a ſluce may come ouer euerie roote being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with earth: this roote bringeth forth ſundrie canes, and ſo conſequently all the reſt. It groweth two yeares before the yéelding of profit, and not ſixe monethes, as <hi>Andrew Theuet</hi> the French man wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</p>
               <p>Then are they cut euen with the ground, and the tops and leaues called <hi>Coholia</hi> cut off, and the canes bound into bundels like faggets, &amp; ſo are carried to the ſugar houſe called <hi>Iugenio,</hi> where they are ground in a mill, and the iuyce thereof conuayed by conduct to a great veſſell made for the purpoſe, where it is boyled till it waxe thicke, and then is it put into a fornaice or earthen pots of the moulde of a Sugar loafe, &amp; then is it carryed to another houſe,
<pb facs="tcp:13041:6"/>
called a purging houſe, where it is placed to purge the blacknes with a certain clay that is laid thereon. Of the remainder in the cauldron is made a ſecond ſort called <hi>Eſcumas,</hi> and of the purging liquor that droppeth from the white Sugar is made a third ſort, and the remainder is called <hi>Panela</hi> or <hi>Netas,</hi> the refuſe of all the purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is called <hi>Remiel</hi> or <hi>Mallaſſes:</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is made another ſort called <hi>Refinnado.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When this firſt fruit is in this ſorte gathered called <hi>Planta,</hi> then the Cane field where it grew, is burned ouer with Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſtraw to the ſtumps of the firſt canes, and being huſbanded, watred &amp; trimmed, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of other two yeres, it yéeldeth the ſecond fruite called <hi>Zoca.</hi> The third fruite is called <hi>Tercia Zoca,</hi> the fourth <hi>Quarta Zoca,</hi> and ſo orderly the reſt till age cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the olde Canes to be planted againe.</p>
               <p>This Iland hath ſingular good wine, eſpecially in the towne of <hi>Telde,</hi> and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie ſortes of good frutes, as Batata, Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, peares, Apples, Orenges, Lemmons. Pomegranads, Figs, Peaches of diuerſe ſortes, and many other fruites: but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye the <hi>Plantano</hi> which groweth néere brooke ſides, it is a trée that hath no Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:13041:7"/>
in it, but groweth directly vpward w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodie hauing maruailous thick leaues, &amp; euery leafe at the toppe of two yeardes long and almoſt halfe a yearde broade.</p>
               <p>The Trée neuer yéeldeth fruite but once, and then is cut down, in whoſe place ſpringeth another, and ſo ſtill continueth. The fruit groweth on a braunch, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie trée yéeldeth two or thrée of thoſe bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which beareth ſome more and ſome leſſe, as ſome 40. and ſome 30. the fruit is like a Cowcumber, and when it is ripe it is blacke, and in eating more delicate then anye conſerue. This Ilande is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlye prouided of Oxen Kine, Camelles, Goates, ſhéepe, Capons, Hens, Ducks, and Pidgeons, and great Partridges. Woode is the thing that moſt wanteth: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue perticularly to deale of the other ſixe Ilands, I leaue further inlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Canaria,</hi> which ſtandeth in 27. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées diſtant from the <hi>Aequator.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="description_of_island">
               <head>The Ile of Tenerif.</head>
               <p>THE Iland of <hi>Tenerif</hi> ſtandeth in 27. degrées &amp; a halfe, from the equator, &amp; is diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Canaria</hi> 12. leagues, Northward.
<pb facs="tcp:13041:7"/>
This Ilande conteineth 17. leagues in length, and the land lyeth high in forme of a ridge of ſowen lande in ſome parte of <hi>England,</hi> and in the middeſt of the ſayde place ſtandeth a round hill called <hi>Pico De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teythe,</hi> ſcituated of this ſort. The toppe of this pike conteineth of height directly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward 15. leagues and more, which is 45. Engliſh miles, out of the which often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times procéedeth fire and brimſtone, &amp; may be about halfe a mile compaſſe: the ſayde toppe is in forme or likeneſſe of a caldron. But within two miles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> top is nothing but aſhes and pomiſh ſtones: yet beneath that two miles, is the colde region couered all the yeare with Snowe, and ſomewhat lower are mightie huge trées growing called <hi>Vinatico</hi> which is excéeding heauie, and will not rot in anie water, although it lye a thouſand yéeres therein. Alſo there is a wood called <hi>Barbuſano,</hi> of like vertue, with many Sauine trées and Pine trées. And beneath this ſorts of trées are woods of Baie trées, of x. &amp; 12. miles long, which is a pleaſant thing to trauaile through, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which are great numbers of ſmall birdes, which ſing excéeding ſwéete: but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially one ſort that are verie little, and
<pb facs="tcp:13041:8"/>
of coulour in all reſpects like a Swallow, ſauing he hath a little blacke ſpot on his breaſt as broade as a pennie. He ſingeth more ſwéeter then all the reſt, but if he be taken and impriſoned in a cage, he liueth but a ſmall while. This Iland bringeth forth all ſortes of fruites as <hi>Canaria</hi> doth, and alſo all the other Ilands in generall, bringeth forth ſhrubbes or bruſhes, out of the which iſſueth a iuyce as white as milke, which after a while that it hath come out waxeth thicke, and is excéeding good Birdlime, the buſh is called <hi>Taybay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba.</hi> This Iland alſo bringeth forth another trée called <hi>Drago,</hi> which groweth on high among rockes, and by inciſſion at the foote of the trée iſſueth out a liquor like bloud, &amp; is a common drugge among Apothecaries. Of the wood of this trée are made targets greatly eſtéemed, becauſe if anie ſword or dagger hit thereon, they ſticke ſo faſt that it is hard plucking them out.</p>
               <p>This is the moſt fruitfulleſt Iland of all the reſt for corne, and in that reſpect is a mother or nurſe to al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> others in time of néed. There groweth alſo a certaine moſſe vpon the high rockes called <hi>Orchel,</hi> which is bought for Diars to die withall. There
<pb facs="tcp:13041:8"/>
are 12. <hi>Ingenios</hi> called ſugar houſes, which make great quantitie of Sugar.</p>
               <p>There is alſo one league of grounde which ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth betwéene two towns, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one called <hi>Larotaua,</hi> &amp; the other <hi>Rialeio,</hi> which is thought that the like plot of ground is not in all the world. The reaſon is, that this one league of ground produceth ſwéet water out of the cliffes or rockie moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, corne of all ſortes, fruites of all ſortes, and excellent good ſilke, flaxe, waxe, and honnie, and verie good wines in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, with great ſtore of Sugar and fire woode. Out of this Iland is laden greate quantitie of wines for the weſt <hi>India,</hi> and other Countries. The beſt groweth on a hill ſide called the <hi>Ramble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is in that Iland a faire Citie, ſtanding thrée leagues from the ſea, néere vnto a lake called <hi>Laguna,</hi> wherin are two faire Pariſh Churches, there dwelleth the gouernour who ruleth al that Iland with iuſtice. There are alſo Aldermen for the publike weale, who buy their offices of the king: the moſt of the whole inhabitants of this Citie are Gentlemen, Merchants, and huſband men.</p>
               <p>There are other foure Townes called
<pb facs="tcp:13041:9"/>
                  <hi>Sancta Crux, Larotaua, Rialeio,</hi> and <hi>Gara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chico?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Iland before the conqueſt dwelt ſeauen kinges, who with all their people dwelt in caues, and were cloathed in goat ſkinnes, as the <hi>Canaria</hi> people were, and with ſuch like order of dyet as they had. Their order of buriall was, that when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie died, he was carried naked to a greate caue, where he was propped vp againſt the wall ſtanding on his féete. But if he were of anie authoritie among them, then had hée a ſtaffe in his hand, &amp; a veſſell of milke ſtanding by him. I haue ſéene caues of 300. of theſe corps together, the fleſh béeing dryed vp, the bodie remained as light as parchment. Theſe people were called <hi>Gua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> by naturall name they ſpake another language cleane contrarie to the <hi>Canari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and ſo conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly euerie Iland ſpake a ſeuerall language. Note gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the Ilande of <hi>Canaria,</hi> the Ile of <hi>Tenerif,</hi> and the Ile of <hi>Palme</hi> appertaine to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> vnto whome they rent fiftie thouſand Duckets yéerely for cuſtome &amp; other profits. All theſe Ilandes ioyntly are one Biſhoprick, which rent to the Biſhop is 12. thouſand duckets yéerly,
<pb facs="tcp:13041:9"/>
and this I conclude of the Ile of <hi>Tenerif,</hi> which ſtandeth 27. degrées and a halfe, as I haue before declared.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="description_of_island">
               <head>Gomera.</head>
               <p>THe Iland of <hi>Gomera</hi> ſtandeth Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from <hi>Tenerif,</hi> in diſtaunce ſixe leagues: this is but a ſmal Iland contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 8. leagues in length. It is an Earle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the Lord thereof is called, the Earle of <hi>Gomera.</hi> But in caſe of anie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie the vaſſalls may appeale to the kings ſuperiour Iudges which reſide in <hi>Canaria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Iland hath one proper towne, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Gomera,</hi> which hath an excellent good port or harbor for ſhips, where oftentimes the India Fléete, take refreſhing for their voyage.</p>
               <p>There is alſo ſufficient graine and fruit for the maintenaunce of themſelues.</p>
               <p>There is one <hi>Iugenio</hi> or Sugar houſe, with great plentie of wine and other ſorts of fruits, as <hi>Canaria</hi> and <hi>Tenerif</hi> hath.</p>
               <p>This Iland yéeldeth no other commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie but onely Orchell, it ſtandeth in 27. degrées diſtant from the Equator toward
<pb facs="tcp:13041:10"/>
the pole Articke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="description_of_island">
               <head>The Ile of Palma.</head>
               <p>THe Ile of <hi>Palma</hi> ſtandeth. 12. leagues, diſtaunt from thy Ile <hi>Gomera</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſtward. This Iland is fruitfull of wine and Sugar: it hath a proper Citie, called the Citie of <hi>Palma,</hi> where is great contraction for wines, which are laden for the Weſt <hi>India</hi> &amp; other places. This citie hath one faire Church, and a gouernour, &amp; Aldermen to mainetaine and execute iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. It hath alſo another pretie Towne, called <hi>S. Andrewes.</hi> It hath alſo foure <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genios</hi> which make excellent ſugar, two of the which are called <hi>Zauzes,</hi> and the other two, <hi>Taſſacort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Iland gathereth but little bread corne: but rather is thereof prouided from <hi>Tenerif</hi> and other places.</p>
               <p>Their beſt wines grow in a ſoile called the <hi>Brenia,</hi> where yéerely is gathered 12. thouſand Buts of wine like vnto maulm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. This Iland ſtandeth round, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth in circuit néere 25. leagues. It hath plentie of all ſorts of fruits, as <hi>Canaria</hi> &amp; <hi>Tenerif</hi> hath, it ſtandeth in twentie ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:13041:10"/>
degrées and a halfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="description_of_island">
               <head>The Iland of Yron, called Hierro.</head>
               <p>THis Iland ſtandeth 10. leagues diſtant from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iland of <hi>Palma</hi> Weaſtward: it is but a little Ilande, which containeth ſixe leagues in circuite, and hath but ſmall peroblation. It appertayneth to the Earle of <hi>Gomera.</hi> The chiefeſt commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of this Ilande is Goates fleſh and Orchell. There is no Wine in all that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, but onely one vineard that an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh man of <hi>Taunton</hi> in the Weſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie planted among rockes, his name was <hi>Iohn Hill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Iland hath no kinde of freſh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but onely in the middle of the Ilande groweth a great trée with leaues lyke an Oliue trée, which hath a great ſeſterne at the foote of the ſaid trée. This Trée conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually is couered with clowdes, and by meane thereof, the leaues of the ſayde Trée dooeth ſtill droppe Water, verye ſwéete into the ſayd Seſterne, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the ſayd trée from the clowdes by attraction. And this water ſufficeth the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<pb facs="tcp:13041:11"/>
for all neceſſitie, as well the Cattell, as for the inhabitants. It ſtandeth in 27. degrées.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="description_of_island">
               <head>The Iland of Lanzerot.</head>
               <p>THe Ilande of <hi>Lanzerot</hi> ſtandeth xviij. leagues diſtaunt from <hi>Gran Canaria</hi> Southeaſtward, the onely commoditie of this Iland, is Goats fleſh and Orchell. It is an Earldome, &amp; doth appertaine to <hi>Don Auguſtine de Herrera,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> title of Earle of <hi>Fortauentura</hi> &amp; <hi>Lanzerot.</hi> But the vaſſalls of theſe Earledomes, may in any cauſe of wrong, appeale to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kings Iudges, which reſide in <hi>Canaria,</hi> as I haue ſayd before: becauſe although the King hath reſerued to himſelfe but onely the thrée fruitfull I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, called <hi>Canaria, Tenerif,</hi> &amp; <hi>Palma,</hi> yet hée alſo reſerued the rod of iuſtice to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, becauſe otherwiſe the vaſſals might bée euill intreated of their Lords.</p>
               <p>From this Iland is wéekly brought to <hi>Canaria, Tenerif,</hi> &amp; <hi>Palma,</hi> boates laden w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dried Goates fleſh, called <hi>Tuſſinetta,</hi> which ſerueth in ſtéed of bacon, and is very good meate. This Iland ſtandeth in 26. degrées and is in length 12. leagues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="description_of_island">
               <pb facs="tcp:13041:11"/>
               <head>The Ile of Fortauentura.</head>
               <p>THE Ile of <hi>Fortauentura</hi> ſtandeth 50. leagues diſtant from the Promontorie of <hi>Cabo de Guer,</hi> in the firme land of <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica,</hi> and 24. leagues diſtant from <hi>Canana</hi> Eaſtward. This Iland doth appertaine to the Senior of <hi>Lanzerot.</hi> It is reaſonable fruitfull of Wheate and Barly, and alſo of Kine, Goats, and Orchell: this Ile is 15. leagues long and 10. leagues broad on the North ſide. It hath a little Ilande about one league diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maine Iland be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene both of the which it is nauegable for anie ſhips, and is called <hi>Gracioſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Both <hi>Fortauentura</hi> and <hi>Lanzerot</hi> haue verie little wine of the growth of thoſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands. It ſtandeth in 27. degrées.</p>
               <p>Thus much haue I written of theſe 7. Ilands by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, becauſe I was a dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler there as I haue ſayd before, the ſpace of ſeauen yeares, in the affaires of Maſter <hi>Thomas Lock,</hi> Maſter <hi>Anthonie Hikman,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Caſthin,</hi> who in thoſe dayes were worthie Merchants, and of great cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in the citie of <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="description_of_island">
               <head>A deſcription of the Iland of Madera.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13041:12"/>THE Iland of <hi>Madera</hi> ſtandeth in 33. degrées diſtant from the equinoctinall line, and 70. leagues from the Ile of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerif</hi> Northeaſtward, &amp; Southweſt from <hi>Hercules</hi> pillers. This Iland was diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, conquered, &amp; inhabited by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Portingall</hi> nation: it was firſt called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iland of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dera,</hi> by reaſon of the great wilderneſſe of ſundrie ſorts of trées that there did grow, and yet dooth, as Ceder, Cipers, Vinatico, Barbuzano, Pine trées, and diuers others, and therefore the ſayd Iland continueth ſtill with the ſame name. Howbeit they hold opinion that betwéene the ſaid Iland and the Ile of <hi>Palma</hi> is an Iland not yet diſcouered, which is the true Iland <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> called S. <hi>Brandon.</hi> This Iland renteth a great ſum of money to the king of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingal</hi> yéerely: it hath one faire citie called <hi>Fouchall,</hi> which hath a faire port or har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for ſhips, and a ſtrong Bulwarke, &amp; a faire Cathedrall Church, with a Biſhop &amp; other dignities therevnto appertaining. There is alſo iuſtice and gouernment ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Portingal</hi> vſe. But cauſes of appellation are remitted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie of <hi>Liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne</hi> in <hi>Portingal,</hi> to the kings ſuperiour Iudges there. This Iland hath another
<pb facs="tcp:13041:12"/>
towne called <hi>Machico,</hi> which hath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a good rode for ſhips. There is alſo. 16 Sugar houſes called <hi>Ingenios,</hi> which make excellent good Sugar.</p>
               <p>There is beſides the gooly timber before declared, greate ſtore of diuers ſortes of fruites, as peares, apples, plummes, wilde dates, peaches of diuerſe ſortes, Mellons, Batatas, Oringes, Lemons, pomgranads, Cidrons, Figs, and all manner of garden hearbs. Ther are many Dragon trees, ſuch as grow in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Canaria</hi> Ilands. But chiefly this land produceth great quantitie of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular good wines which are laden for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie places. On the North ſide of this land thrée leagues diſtant from the maine I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſtandeth another little Iland, called <hi>Porto ſanto:</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people therof liueth by huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie, for the Iland of <hi>Madera</hi> gathereth but little corne: but rather is thereof pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided out of <hi>Fraunce</hi> and from the Iland of <hi>Tenerif.</hi> On the Eaſt ſide of the Ile of <hi>Madera</hi> ſixe leagues diſtant ſtandeth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther little Iland called the Deſart, which produceth onely Orchell, and nouriſheth a great number of Goates. For the prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the maine Iland, which may be 30. leagues in circuit, and the land is of great
<pb facs="tcp:13041:13"/>
height where thoſe trées grow. It is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſée the conueiance of the water to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Ingenios</hi> by mines through the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines.</p>
               <p>In the midde waie betwéene <hi>Tenerif,</hi> and the Iland of <hi>Madera</hi> ſtandeth a little ſolitarie Iland called the <hi>Saluages,</hi> which may be about one league in compaſſe, which hath neither trée nor fruit, but onely foode for Goates.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13041:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
